<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Eric Brasil</title>
    <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Eric Brasil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ericbrasiln.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Journal articles</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/publications/articles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/publications/articles/</guid>
      <description>List of top publications of recent years  Git como ferramenta metodológica em projetos de História (parte 1), Programming Historian em português 3 (2023), https://doi.org/10.46430/phpt0045. pyHDB - Ferramenta Heurística para a Hemeroteca Digital Brasileira: utilizando técnicas de web scraping para a pesquisa em História. História da Historiografia: International Journal of Theory and History of Historiography, Ouro Preto, v. 15, n. 40, p. 186–217, 2022. DOI The Caribbean Struggle for Freedom - Freedom Roots: Histories from the Caribbean.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New article about pyHDB tool!</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/blog/pyhdb-en/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/blog/pyhdb-en/</guid>
      <description>On the last day of 2022, the new issue of the História da Historiografia journal came out with an article of mine called &amp;ldquo;pyHDB - Ferramenta Heurística para a Hemeroteca Digital Brasileira: utilizando técnicas de web scraping para a pesquisa em História&amp;rdquo;.
It is my darling!
In the article, I present pyHDB, a methodological support tool for research in the Brazilian Digital Newspaper Library, of the National Library. I analyze its relationship with the theory, methodology, and epistemology of history, focusing on the selection, collection, organization, and criticism of sources.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Novo artigo sobre a ferramenta pyHDB!</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/blog/pyhdb-pt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/blog/pyhdb-pt/</guid>
      <description>No último dia de 2022 saiu novo número da Revista História da Historiografia com um artigo meu chamado &amp;ldquo;pyHDB - Ferramenta Heurística para a Hemeroteca Digital Brasileira: utilizando técnicas de web scraping para a pesquisa em História&amp;rdquo;.
É meu xodó!
No artigo apresento a pyHDB, ferramenta de suporte metodológico para a pesquisa na Hemeroteca Digital Brasileira, da Biblioteca Nacional. Analiso sua relação com teoria, metodologia e epistemologia da história, focando na seleção, coleta, organização e critica das fontes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital Tools</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/teaching/tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/teaching/tools/</guid>
      <description>Brazilian Humanities Digital Repository - REDHBR Access the page here!
REDHBR aggregates codes for automated data collection regarding the main events and associations in the humanities area in Brazil.
Scripts, databases and all documents are available and can be downloaded with just one click.
pyHDB - Heuristic tool for the Brazilian Digital Newspaper Library Access the tool here
Methodological aid tool for research in the Brazilian Digital Newspaper Library of the National Library.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Books and chapters</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/publications/books/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/publications/books/</guid>
      <description>List of top publications of recent years.  BRASIL, E.; NASCIMENTO, L. F. A ferramenta de busca da Hemeroteca Digital da Brasileira e o ofício do historiador: reflexões para a história digital. In: Nicodemo; Rota; Marino (orgs.). Caminhos da História Digital no Brasil. 1ed. Vitória, ES: Editora Milflores, 2022, p. 209-252. BRASIL, Eric; NASCIMENTO, Leonardo. Por uma História Social Digital: o uso do CAQDAS na pesquisa e escrita da Históra. In: BARROS, José D’Assunção (Org.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Classes and Courses</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/teaching/courses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/teaching/courses/</guid>
      <description>Websites and presentations of courses and classes   Course: CCLHM0069 - Introdução à História Digital - 2021.1
  Course: CCLHM0057 - História da América: colonização e resistência - 2021.1
  Course: CCLHM0057 - História da América: colonização e resistência - 2020.1
  Course: BHUM0004 - Processos coloniais e a construação da modernidade - 2020.1
  Course: Ferramentas Digitais e a pesquisa em Humanidades - Plex (2020)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/contact/</guid>
      <description>E-mails:  ericbrasiln@proton.me profericbrasil@unilab.edu.br  Linktree Lattes - Orcid - ResearchGate - Academia.edu - GitHub - Twitter - Mastodon</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentations, workshops, tutorials</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/teaching/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/teaching/materials/</guid>
      <description>Material for presentations, round tables and lectures   Criação, manutenção e divulgação de projetos de História em meios digitais: git, GitHub e o Programming Historian. Material para o Webinar LHUD - FGV/CPDOC. DOI
  Hemeroteca Digital Brasileira e a pesquisa histórica: reflexões sobre teoria e prática. Material para o curso e-história da Educação da UFRN. DOI
  Dá pra pesquisar o Caribe do Brasil? Reflexões teórico-metodológicas. Material para a mesa promovida pelo Canal da América - 2020-11-30, 17h.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roundtables and Lectures</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/talks/lectures/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/talks/lectures/</guid>
      <description>2022 Criação, manutenção e divulgação de projetos de História em meios digitais: git, GitHub e o Programming Historian. Webinar LHUD - FGV/CPDOC
DOI
  Hemeroteca Digital Brasileira e a pesquisa histórica: reflexões sobre teoria e prática. Curso e-história da Educação da UFRN
DOI
  2021 SESSÃO ESPECIAL – História Digital - 7ª JORNADA DE PESQUISADORES DA FBN   Web Scraping e a construção de datasets para a pesquisa histórica na era digital: aspectos técnicos, metodológicos e epistemológicos No simpósio temático - História, Arquivos e Arquivamento na era digital, do IIIEPTH</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summarized curriculum</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/cv/</guid>
      <description>Professor of the undergraduate courses in History and Humanities at the Institute of Humanities and Languages at the University for the International Integration of Afro-Brazilian Lusophony (IHLM/UNILAB), Malês campus, Bahia, Brazil (2017 - current).
Coordinator of the undergraduate course in History at the same institute from 2019 to 2020.
Visiting Researcher at the Digital Humanities Lab, IHC, FSCH-NOVA, Lisbon, Portugal.
Professor of the Multidisciplinary Graduate Program in Ethnic and African Studies (POSAFRO) at the Federal University of Bahia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New website / Novo Site</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/blog/my-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 22:44:04 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/blog/my-first-post/</guid>
      <description>Personal website update for HUGO with the theme created by rhazdon.
Atualização do site pessoal para HUGO com o tema criado por rhazdon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Completed research projects</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/projects/completed/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/projects/completed/</guid>
      <description>Maintaining, creating and publishing digital history projects: the case of Programming Historian. Summary: This project aims to analyze the Programming Historian guidelines, structure, and workflow, both on the website and in the organization&amp;rsquo;s GitHub repositories. As a result, will be produced reports about the current state of the technical architecture of the PH and its documentation, as well as a set of recommendations for the correction of errors and some improvements, mainly in portuguese version, and a original lesson in portuguese.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research projects in progress</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/projects/in-progress/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/projects/in-progress/</guid>
      <description>Métodos, ferramentas e repositórios digitais em português: um framework para a pesquisa em periódicos digitalizados Summary: O objetivo do projeto é analisar a operação historiográfica relacionada ao processo de selecionar, recolher e organizar fontes primárias por meio de ferramentas e dados digitais. Terá como foco repositórios e interfaces gráficas que permitem o acesso a periódicos da imprensa de língua portuguesa digitalizados, com destaque para a Hemeroteca Digital Brasileira e a coleção de periódicos da Biblioteca Nacional Digital de Portugal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Video Lessons</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/talks/video-lessons/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/talks/video-lessons/</guid>
      <description>Full Course &amp;lsquo;Intro to Digital History&amp;rsquo;: 
Full Course &amp;lsquo;Digital Tools and Research in Humanities. 
Workshop &amp;lsquo;An introduction to Markdown and its possibilities for teaching and scientific divulgation&amp;rsquo;   </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
