<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teachings on Eric Brasil</title>
    <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/teaching/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Teachings on Eric Brasil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ericbrasiln.github.io/teaching/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Digital Tools</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/teaching/tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/teaching/tools/</guid>
      <description>Brazilian Humanities Digital Repository - REDHBR Access the page here!
REDHBR aggregates codes for automated data collection regarding the main events and associations in the humanities area in Brazil.
Scripts, databases and all documents are available and can be downloaded with just one click.
pyHDB - Heuristic tool for the Brazilian Digital Newspaper Library Access the tool here
Methodological aid tool for research in the Brazilian Digital Newspaper Library of the National Library.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Classes and Courses</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/teaching/courses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/teaching/courses/</guid>
      <description>Websites and presentations of courses and classes   Course: CCLHM0069 - Introdução à História Digital - 2021.1
  Course: CCLHM0057 - História da América: colonização e resistência - 2021.1
  Course: CCLHM0057 - História da América: colonização e resistência - 2020.1
  Course: BHUM0004 - Processos coloniais e a construação da modernidade - 2020.1
  Course: Ferramentas Digitais e a pesquisa em Humanidades - Plex (2020)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentations, workshops, tutorials</title>
      <link>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/teaching/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericbrasiln.github.io/teaching/materials/</guid>
      <description>Material for presentations, round tables and lectures   Criação, manutenção e divulgação de projetos de História em meios digitais: git, GitHub e o Programming Historian. Material para o Webinar LHUD - FGV/CPDOC. DOI
  Hemeroteca Digital Brasileira e a pesquisa histórica: reflexões sobre teoria e prática. Material para o curso e-história da Educação da UFRN. DOI
  Dá pra pesquisar o Caribe do Brasil? Reflexões teórico-metodológicas. Material para a mesa promovida pelo Canal da América - 2020-11-30, 17h.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
